Guide to the William R. Perl papers, 1925-1998 MS2026
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
William R. Perl papers
1925-1998
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Perl, William R.
MS2026
5 Linear Feet
The William R. Perl Papers document the education, professional career and social activism of William R. Perl (1906-1998).
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
Collection donated by Lore Perl in 1999.
Historical or Biographical Note
William Raphael Perl was born in Prague on September 21, 1906 in what was then the Austro-Hungarian Empire. Much of his youth and early manhood was spent in Vienna. As a student at the University of Vienna, Perl joined Ivria, one of several Jewish fraternities, and soon became deeply immersed in the growing Zionist movement. After earning a Ph.D. in Law and a Master's degree in International Business, he practiced law in Vienna until the Nazi take-over in 1938.
A protégé of the revisionist Zionist leader Vladimir Jabotinsky, Perl became increasingly concerned and active in attempting to safeguard Jews from the violent Nazi campaign against them. In 1938 he organized "Die Aktion," a circle of young Viennese Zionists dedicated to making Theodore Herzl's dream of an independent Jewish state a reality. Less than a year later, Die Aktion succeeded in landing a number of "illegal" Jewish immigrants on the coast of then British-controlled Palestine (now Israel). This daring move is believed to have been the first successful landing of such refugees, when almost every other escape route had been closed to them.
It was also the beginning of one of the most remarkable and daring refugee movements in modern history. Working with Zionist groups and Greek smugglers, Perl organized large-scale illegal immigration of Jews to Palestine and prodded reluctant Jewish leaders into doing the same. Often just one step ahead of the Gestapo and of the British agents determined to stop illegal immigration, Perl rescued an estimated forty thousand European Jews from annihilation by the Nazis. The gripping history of that rescue is told in Dr. Perl's own words in his books, The Four Front War and Operation Action.
In 1938 Perl married Lore Rollig, an equally brave Viennese woman who converted to Judaism that year. Their marriage was a closely guarded secret because Nazi law treated such intermarriage as a serious crime. In 1940, Perl managed to reach the United States and was working to arrange for Lore to join him when Nazi Germany declared war on the United States and hope of her rescue was dashed. In 1943 Lore Perl was arrested for aiding Jewish children and was sent to Ravensbruck concentration camp.
Perl joined the U.S. Army in 1941 and distinguished himself as a military intelligence officer. By a twist of fate, he was assigned to Allied Intelligence in London, where he worked with some of the same British intelligence officers who had pursued him across Europe. In 1945 he risked court-martial and imprisonment to rescue Lore from Vienna, then under Russian command.
After the war, Perl played a key role in the prosecution of Col. Joachim Peiper and other members of the Waffen SS for the murder of American prisoners of war at Malmedy, Belgium in December 1944. The Perls settled in the United States with their two young sons, Raphael and Solomon. Dr. Perl continued his study of psychology at Columbia University and then served as an army psychologist until his retirement with the rank of Lt. Colonel in 1966.
In the early 1970s Perl received international media attention for his dramatic protests against persecution of Jews by the Soviet Union. As head of the Washington branch of the Jewish Defense League, Perl organized demonstrations outside and inside the Soviet Embassy and at public events involving Soviet officials. These activities lead to his arrest and conviction in federal court in November 1976.
In 1989, Perl's third book, The Holocaust Conspiracy, was published giving a detailed account of conscious efforts by key figures in the United States, Great Britain, Switzerland, the Soviet Union and other nations to prevent the escape of Jews from Nazi-dominated Europe. Though stricken with Parkinson's disease, Dr. Perl remained active in Jewish affairs until his last days. On December 24, 1998, Dr. William Perl died at his home to the intense grief of his family, thousands of friends and grateful beneficiaries of his daring spirit. Of the many tributes he received throughout his lifetime, perhaps the most fitting is the one given in the preface to The Four Front War by Israel's then-Prime Minister, Menachem Begin:
"Your deeds, Dr. Perl, will be remembered forever by the Jewish people, indeed, by all people of good will."
Collection Scope and Content
The William R. Perl Papers document the education, professional career and social activism of William R. Perl (1906-1998). The collection is stored in 10 manuscript boxes, 1 audio cassette box and 1 oversized box. A large portion of the collection consists of undated photocopies and photostats of original documents. The Papers are arranged into eight series: Biographical Files, Jewish Activism Files, Military Service Files, Professional Files, Legal Files, Miscellaneous Writings, Miscellaneous Correspondence, and Mixed Media. In terms of physical extent, the largest series are the Jewish Activism Files and the Military Service Files.
Earliest records in this collection relate to William R. Perl's high school and university education (1920s). Obituaries of Perl (1998) are the most recent documents. However, the bulk of the William R. Perl Papers date from the 1940s (after Perl emigrated to the United States), through the 1980s (when Perl received increased recognition for his work during the Holocaust). Early papers (and papers relating to the earlier part of Perl's life) are often written in German, while most papers dating after 1941 are in English.
Of particular interest to researchers are correspondence, copies of official documents, artifacts and other materials relating to Perl's involvement in transporting European Jewish refugees to Palestine. These papers are filed in the Rescue of European Jews Files sub-series of the Jewish Activism Series. To understand the context of the items, researchers are strongly urged to read Reuven Schlenker and Charles Goolsby's manuscript The World of Willi Perl, Perl's own books The Four Front War and Operation Action, clippings in the various Newsclippings sub-series of the Perl Papers, and other biographical treatments of Perl. Such secondary readings will help the researcher fill intellectual gaps and determine the basic facts of events prior to using original materials in the rest of the collection.
Also of note are affidavits and photographs of German soldiers who participated in the "massacre" of American soldiers in Malmedy, Belgium in 1944. Though many of the affidavits are incomplete photocopies of originals and their authors could not always be identified by the Manuscripts Librarian, some affidavits are original documents which may not have been accessible to the public until now. Most of the affidavits are handwritten in old German script (making them difficult to read) but for some documents a typewritten English translation is available. Whenever possible, the Manuscripts Librarian has identified the author and date of affidavits and listed such information in the Container List of this finding aid.
There are several notable gaps in the coverage of the William R. Perl Papers. There is little documentation of Perl's life prior to his emigration to the United States, though a major exception are documents relating to Perl's rescue of European Jews. The Perl Papers also contain little documentation of Perl's career as a psychologist (ca. 1950-1968) other than newsclippings and Perl's own writings and public speeches. Other than one folder of correspondence and some flyers and photographs, there is little evidence (meeting minutes or notes) about the Jewish Defense League, of which Perl was President. Most of the Correspondence files in the collection contain only one letter to or from a given correspondent, and many folders relating to Perl's public speeches and honors only contain a program, letter or other ephemeral item. Lastly, the Papers contain very little information about Perl's wife, Lore (Rollig) Perl, their children, or other members of the Perl family. Again, researchers are encouraged to consult secondary sources and other repositories for further information about the life and times of William R. Perl.
The National Archives and Records Administration (Washington, D.C.), the Simon Wiesenthal Center (Los Angeles), and the Public Records Office (Kew, Surrey, England) are three known repositories that have documentation relating to Perl's activities (copies of documents from these repositories can be found in the Perl Papers). The National Archives has documentation of War Crimes trials at Dachau, contained in Record Group 111 (United States Department of Defense, United States Army), Record Group 331 (Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers, Judge Advocate Section, War Crimes Division) and other record groups. To date, the Manuscripts Librarian could not find information about relevant archival holdings at the Wiesenthal Center or the Public Records Office. Upon their arrival to the Special Collections Department, the William R. Perl Papers were largely unarranged (though some documents were grouped by topic), and the provenance of some documents was uncertain or difficult to establish. In order to make the Perl Papers more usable to researchers, the Manuscripts Librarian identified different aspects of Perl's career (e.g., Jewish Activism, Military Service, etc.). as series for the Papers. Thereunder, items documenting similar kinds of activities (writings, speeches, correspondence, etc.), were grouped together, and thereunder, most documents were arranged in chronological order. One exception to chronological arrangement are Correspondence sub-series, which are arranged alphabetically by last name of correspondent.
Out of concerns for preservation, photographs, audio recordings and oversized materials were organized as a separate, "Mixed Media" series, and grouped together by media. As a preservation measure, most original newsclippings have been photocopied onto acid-free paper. Photographs have been placed in mylar sleeves to protect them from handling.
Several books were donated with the William R. Perl Papers:
Merlin, Samuel. Jabotinsky Returns to the Land of Israel. Tel-Aviv: Hadar Publishing Company, 1965. Seewann, Harald. Theodor Herzl und die Akademische Jugend. Graz: H. Seewann, 1998 (2 copies). Seewann, Harald. Zirkel und Zionsstern: Bilder und Dokumente aus der versunkenen Welt des Jüdisch Nationalen Korporationswesens: ein Beitrag zur Geschichte des Zionismus auf Akademischem Boden. Graz: Harald Seewann, 1992 (2 copies).
These were removed from the collection, cataloged individually and shelved in the Special Collections Department's general stacks.
In the container list, the designation "n.d." is used to mark folders that contain undated documents, and such documents are filed at the end of folders. "WRP" is used to designate William R. Perl. The terms "unidentified" "unattributed" and "illegible" are used when a good-faith effort on the part of the Manuscripts Librarian to determine speakers, authors, or other identifying information failed.
Collection Organization
Organized into eight series: Biographical files, Jewish activism files, Military service files, Professional files, Legal files, Miscellaneous writings, Miscellaneous correspondence, and Mixed media.
Vienna (Austria); Political activists; Zionism; Audiocassettes; United States; Jewish activism; Photographs; Rescues; Biography; Perl, William R.
- Biographical files, 1920-1998; MS2026 Series 1; 0.25 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  The Biographical Files series consists of 11 folders of documents which summarize facts about the life, education and career of William R. Perl. Records span from the 1920s (Perl's early education) through 1998 (Perl's death). Documents are grouped by topic with folders arranged in chronological order.
  The Biographical Files are divided into two groups, Reference Files and Education Records. The Reference Files contains vital records, curriculum vitae, obituaries and biographical writings about Perl dating from 1946 to 1998. Of note to users is the 152-page manuscript "The World of Willi Perl" by Charles Goolsby and Reuven Schlenker, an extensive treatment of William R. Perl's life. The Education Records sub-series contain course schedules, grade reports and term papers dating from 1925-1960. Researchers using this series should consult the Mixed Media series for portraits of Perl and his wife, Lore.
  - Reference Files: Vital Records, 1946-1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Reference Files: Curriculum Vitae, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Reference Files: Articles about WRP in general reference sources [text], 1973-1987 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Reference Files: The World of Willy Perl [text] by Charles Goolsby and Reuven Schlenker, 1995-1998 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Reference Files: Obituaries, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Education Records: Courses taken, 1925-1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Education Records: Igul-Officials [text] v.3:no.1, 1940 May-1940 June (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Education Records: Courses taken, 1950-1960 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Education Records: Notes for course, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Education Records: "Certain Aspects of the Ego and the Self Expressed and Projected through Handwriting,", 1951 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Education Records: "On Work Satisfaction,", undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Jewish activism files, 1930-1990; MS2026 Series 2; 1 Linear foot
  The Jewish Activism Files series consists material documenting William R. Perl's actions and advocacy on behalf of Jews worldwide. Records span from the late 1930s through the 1990s, though the bulk of records date from 1937-45 and 1968-96. The Jewish Activism Files are arranged into seven groups: Rescue of European Jews Files; Writings; Speeches and Statements; Correspondence; Press Releases, Pamphlets and Broadsides; Awards and Honors; and Newsclippings. Unless otherwise noted, documents in this series are grouped by topic, with folders arranged chronologically. Researchers using this series should consult the Mixed Media series for related photographs, audio recordings and other items.
  The Rescue of European Jews material contains 20 folders of original correspondence, copies of official (mostly British) government documents and correspondence, artifacts and newsclippings relating to the covert transport of European Jews to Palestine during the late 1930s and early 1940s. The Rescue of European Jews sub-series also contains later notes and accounts of the transport. Many of the documents in the Rescue of European Jews sub-series are in German and other foreign languages.
  The Writings materials (23 folders) consists primarily of journal articles on Jewish issues written by William R. Perl, dating from 1945 to 1996 (bulk 1968-1996). The Writings sub-series also contains correspondence and clippings related to Perl's writings, particularly his books The Four-Front War, Operation Action, and The Holocaust Conspiracy.
  The Speeches and Statements materials (17 folders) documents speeches and talks advocating Jewish causes given by William R. Perl. The bulk of items in this sub-series date from the 1970s and later. In some cases, the full text of Perl's speech is not available--- speeches are documented by notes, an announcement or program, a letter, a newsclipping or other ephemeral item.
  The Correspondence materials consists of 17 folders of mostly original correspondence, dating from 1941 to 1995 (bulk 1965-1980). Most folders contain a single letter to or from a correspondent. Of note in this sub-series are letters to and from Jewish leaders Menachem Begin and Meir Kahane, and a folder of correspondence relating to the Jewish Defense League. Folders in this sub-series are arranged alphabetically by last name of correspondent.
  The Press Releases, Pamphlets and Broadsides materials consist of 13 folders of posters, flyers, press releases and other documents meant for broad distribution. The bulk of the materials are authored by the Jewish Defense League, dating ca. 1969-1974. Many of the documents in this sub-series are undated. Folders in this sub-series are arranged alphabetically by the name of the group which authored or distributed the document.
  The Awards and Honors materials (8 folders) document awards and tributes conferred on Perl in appreciation for his advocacy on behalf of Jews. All datable materials in this series date from 1980 to 1998. This sub-series consists of ceremony programs, newsclippings, related correspondence and occasionally, the award itself.
  The Newsclippings materials (19 folders) consist mainly of photocopies of newsclippings that document Perl's activities. The bulk of clippings date from 1968-1987. Newsclippings from Der Judenstatt, the Washington Post, Jewish Week, the Baltimore Sun and other publications are included.
  - Rescue of European Jews Files: Correspondence between Lore Rollig and WRP, 1937-1941 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Rescue of European Jews Files: Correspondence, 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Rescue of European Jews Files: Passports and letters of reference, 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Rescue of European Jews Files: Liberian visas for European Jews, 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Rescue of European Jews Files: Official documents and correspondence, 1938-1944 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Rescue of European Jews Files: Miscellaneous documents, 1938-1943 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Rescue of European Jews Files: Diary/log, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Rescue of European Jews Files: Emigration from Klowdowa, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Rescue of European Jews Files: Sakarya, 1939-1989 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Rescue of European Jews Files: WRP's emigration to the United States, 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Rescue of European Jews Files: Clippings, 1937-1990 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Rescue of European Jews Files: Smuggling Lore Rollig out of Austria, 1945-1953 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Rescue of European Jews Files: Letter from Wolf Weisl, 1962 December 25 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Rescue of European Jews Files: Letter from M. Sobotka, 1974 July 23 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Rescue of European Jews Files: Letter from Kurt, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Rescue of European Jews Files: Interview with Reuben Hecht, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Rescue of European Jews Files: Correspondence between WRP and Harald Seewann, 1995-1998 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Rescue of European Jews Files: Memorandum to Adolph Eichman, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Rescue of European Jews Files: Ships and route used in transport, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Rescue of European Jews Files: Description of WRP's activities, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Writings: "Besuch in Wien." Aufbau Reconstruction. v.11:no.31, 1945 August 03 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Writings: Maariv, 1968 August 31 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Writings: Four Front War, 1975-1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Writings: Four Front War and Operation Action, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Writings: Four Front War and Operation Action, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Writings: Four Front War and Operation Action, 1985-1998 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Writings: "Kissinger's Diplomacy: Leading to Peace or a Holocaust." American Zionist v.64:no.8, 1974 June (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Writings: "'I am Abdul Ibn Youssuf Khoury': The War of the Minds: How to Win It and How to Lose It." Times of Israel and World Jewish Review v.1:no.11, 1975 April (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Writings: "Thoughts.", 1977 July 15 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Writings: "A Painful Decision for Israel." The Jewish Week, 1977 December 01-07 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Writings: Holocaust Conspiracy], 1987-1996 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Writings: "Re. Nazi Propaganda and the Present State [of Mis-Information] Regarding Israel.", 1988 January 06 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Writings: Chicago Tribune, 1989 April 16 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Writings: Commentary, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Writings: "By Oversimplifying Kristallnacht, You Let the World Go Blameless." Washington Post, 1988 November 19 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Writings: "The Holocaust and the Lost Caribbean Paradise." The Freeman: Ideas on Liberty v. 42:no.1, 1992 January (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Writings: "A Jewish Self-Help Undertaking that Saved Forty-Thousand- 'A Pictorial Report.'", 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Writings: "Paradise Denied,", 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Writings: "Paradise Denied: The State Department and the Caribbean, and the Jews of Europe." National Interest no.42 Win., 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Writings: Giacolone, Michael, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Writings: "A Different View of the Holocaust,", undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Writings: New York Journal American, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Writings: Los Angeles Times Magazine, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Speeches and Statements: Speech given at founding of the New Zionist Organization, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Speeches and Statements: "A Need for Jewish Activism Now,", 1967 September 11 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Speeches and Statements: "Has the Second Holocaust Already Begun?,", 1974 March 03 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Speeches and Statements: Statement before the U.S. Senate Committee on Foreign Affairs, 1975 October 06 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Speeches and Statements: Speech before the Free Masons, 1976 March 07 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Speeches and Statements: Radio program, 1983 December 23 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Speeches and Statements: "Talk on Yom Hashoa at Simon Wiesenthal Center,", 1984 April 29 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Speeches and Statements: "The Holocaust Conspiracy,", 1985 November 07 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Speeches and Statements: "The Holocaust Conspiracy,", 1985 November 12 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Speeches and Statements: Speech given at Capitol Hill reception, 1987 May 28 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Speeches and Statements: Speech given to students at the University of Maryland, 1987 April 18 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Speeches and Statements: Speech for "Sakaria Jubilee,", 1990 June 05 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Speeches and Statements: Speech for Days of Remembrance Holocaust Commemoration, 1996 April 17 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Speeches and Statements: Statement to Voice of America, 1996 April 21 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Speeches and Statements: Partial draft of speech, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Speeches and Statements: Partial draft of open letter, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Speeches and Statements: Correspondence regarding other speeches and statements, 1973-1981 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence regarding the Eichman case, 1941-1961 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence regarding the Jewish Defense League, 1973-1994 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence: Arens, Yigal, 1988 March 15 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence: Begin, Menachem, 1973-1980 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence: Bernstein, Nahum A., 1950 July 10 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence: Block, Anne, 1972 August 09 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence: Dinnerstein, Larry, 1974 January 21 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence: Epstein, Beinish, 1963-1970 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence: Epstein, Helen, 1964 June 28 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence: Jabotinsky, Zeev, 1973 June 30 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence: Hecht, Reuben, 1987 May 19 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence: Kahane, Meir, 1973-1980 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence: Margolis, Gerald, 1995 May 26 (Box 3, Folder 30)